<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jboss | Harald Pehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/blog/categories/jboss/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-25T09:24:46+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hpehl.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harald Pehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harald.pehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Send Mails from OpenShift]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpehl.info/send-mails-from-openshift.html"/>
    <updated>2013-08-04T19:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpehl.info/send-mails-from-openshift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenShift is a great place to host your applications. In this post I'm going to show you how you can easily send mails
from your JEE applications running on JBoss. For sending mails I'm going to configure an external SMTP server. Any SMTP
server will do, I'm going to use GMail.<!-- more --></p>

<p>In case you don't already have an application ready, create one selecting the JBoss AS 7 cartridge. Clone the git
repository and open the JBoss standalone configuration: <code>.openshift/config/standalone.xml</code>. Look for the mail subsystem
which should look like this:</p>

<p>```xml
<subsystem xmlns="urn:jboss:domain:mail:1.0"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;mail-session jndi-name="java:jboss/mail/Default"&gt;
    &lt;smtp-server outbound-socket-binding-ref="mail-smtp"/&gt;
&lt;/mail-session&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></subsystem>
```</p>

<p>We're going to add another mail session / smtp server using GMail:</p>

<p>```xml
<subsystem xmlns="urn:jboss:domain:mail:1.0"></p>

<pre><code>...
&lt;mail-session jndi-name="java:/mail/Gmail" from="your.name@gmail.com"&gt;
    &lt;smtp-server ssl="true" outbound-socket-binding-ref="gmail-smtp"&gt;
        &lt;login name="your.name@gmail.com" password="..."/&gt;
    &lt;/smtp-server&gt;
&lt;/mail-session&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></subsystem>
```</p>

<p>Enter your credentials for the SMTP server you want to use. In case you have activated application specific passwords
in your Google profile, the password is not your Google password, but an application specific one you have to create
first.</p>

<p>As you can see we're referencing a named socket binding, which we're going to create now. Towards the end of the
standalone configuration you can see all configured socket bindings:</p>

<p>```xml
<socket-binding-group name="standard-sockets" default-interface="public" port-offset="0"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;socket-binding name="http" port="8080"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="jacorb" interface="unsecure" port="3528"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="jacorb-ssl" interface="unsecure" port="3529"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="jgroups-tcp" port="7600"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="management-native" interface="management" port="9999"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="management-http" interface="management" port="9990"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="messaging" port="5445"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="messaging-throughput" port="5455"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="osgi-http" interface="management" port="8090"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="remoting" port="4447"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="txn-recovery-environment" port="4712"/&gt;
&lt;socket-binding name="txn-status-manager" port="4713"/&gt;
&lt;outbound-socket-binding name="mail-smtp"&gt;
    &lt;remote-destination host="localhost" port="25"/&gt;
&lt;/outbound-socket-binding&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></socket-binding-group>
```</p>

<p>Add an outbound socket binding for you SMTP server:</p>

<p>```xml
<socket-binding-group name="standard-sockets" default-interface="public" port-offset="0"></p>

<pre><code>...
&lt;outbound-socket-binding name="gmail-smtp" source-port="0" fixed-source-port="false"&gt;
    &lt;remote-destination host="smtp.gmail.com" port="465"/&gt;
&lt;/outbound-socket-binding&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></socket-binding-group>
```</p>

<p>We're almost done! Now you can use the mail session in your application. In my case I'm using the mail session from an
<a href="http://www.jboss.org/errai">Errai</a> service, but any other server side class (REST endpoint, servlet, EJB, POJO) should
work also:</p>

<p>```java
import static javax.mail.Message.RecipientType.TO;</p>

<p>import java.util.Date;</p>

<p>import javax.annotation.Resource;
import javax.mail.Address;
import javax.mail.MessagingException;
import javax.mail.Session;
import javax.mail.Transport;
import javax.mail.internet.InternetAddress;
import javax.mail.internet.MimeMessage;</p>

<p>import com.google.common.base.Optional;</p>

<p>import org.jboss.errai.bus.client.api.messaging.Message;
import org.jboss.errai.bus.client.api.messaging.MessageCallback;
import org.jboss.errai.bus.server.annotations.Service;
import org.jboss.errai.common.client.protocols.MessageParts;</p>

<p>@Service
public class FeedbackService implements MessageCallback {</p>

<pre><code>@Resource(mappedName = "java:/mail/Gmail") private Session mailSession;

@Override
public void callback(Message message) {

    // get data out of the message and persist feedback 
    String guest = Optional.fromNullable(message.get(String.class, "guest")).or("n/a");
    boolean commitment = Optional.fromNullable(message.get(Boolean.class, "commitment")).or(false);
    saveFeedback(guest, commitment);

    // send response using the Errai message bus
    // see http://docs.jboss.org/errai/2.4.0.Beta1/errai/reference/html_single/#sid-5931263 
    // for more details
    createConversation(message)
            .subjectProvided()
            .done()
            .reply();

    // sending the mail might take a moment, so this is done *after* sending the response to the client.
    sendMail(guest, commitment);
}

private void saveFeedback(final String guest, final boolean commitment) {
    ...
}

private void sendMail(final String guest, final boolean commitment) {
    try {
        MimeMessage message = new MimeMessage(mailSession);
        Address[] to = new InternetAddress[]{new InternetAddress("your.name@gmail.com")};
        message.setRecipients(TO, to);
        message.setSubject("Your subject");
        message.setContent("Your message", "text/plain");
        Transport.send(message);
    } catch (MessagingException e) {
        // error handling
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>That's all - any feedback, thoughts and objections are welcome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Admin Apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpehl.info/admin-apps.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-18T11:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpehl.info/admin-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you ever wanted to administer your JBoss servers from your iOS or Andoird phone, checkout these great apps from
<a href="https://twitter.com/cvasilak">Christos Vasilakis</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Android: <a href="https://github.com/cvasilak/JBoss-Admin-Android">https://github.com/cvasilak/JBoss-Admin-Android</a></li>
<li>iOS: <a href="http://www.cvasilak.org/JBossAdmin.html">http://www.cvasilak.org/JBossAdmin.html</a> <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/jboss-admin/id523516060?mt=8&uo=4" target="itunes_store"><img src="http://r.mzstatic.com/images/web/linkmaker/badge_appstore-sm.gif" alt="JBoss Admin - Christos Vasilakis" style="border: 0;"/></a></li>
</ul>


<p>Keep it up, Christos!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Independent JBoss Admin Console]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpehl.info/independent-jboss-admin-console.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-05T21:43:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpehl.info/independent-jboss-admin-console</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're currently working on a new feature for the JBoss Admin Console. The console should become independent from the
rest of the JBoss AS distribution. As the console is built with GWT and "merely" consists of static resources like
HTML, JavaScript and CSS, the idea is to have a dedicated host which serves these resources. When loading the console
the user can manage a list of server instances and chooses the one he likes to connect to. The server instances are
stored in the browsers <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webstorage/">local storage</a>, so they will be available the next time the
console is launched:<!-- more --></p>

<p><figure class="centered"><img src="/images/posts/select_server_instance.png" title="Connect to server" ></figure></p>

<p>Using this kind of setup brings us several advantages:</p>

<ul>
<li>We can update the console independently from the rest of the AS code base</li>
<li>We can deploy the console to various (web)app stores like Firefox Marketplace or Chrome Web Store</li>
<li>We can have different console versions with different feature sets (nightly, beta, stable)</li>
<li>Using one console you can connect to different server instances running different setups (development, staging, production)</li>
</ul>


<h1>CORS</h1>

<p>The console talks to the domain controller (DC) using the HTTP management API. Now when the console and the DC live
on different hosts, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same_origin_policy">same origin policy</a> (SOP) throws a monkey
wrench in our efforts. Luckily we're not the first ones confronted with this problem. There are several ways to solve
SOP restrictions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Server Side Proxies</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSONP">JSON with padding</a> (JSONP)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/">Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</a> (CORS)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Client</h2>

<p>According to <a href="http://caniuse.com/#search=cors">caniuse.com</a> CORS is implemented in most of the browsers. CORS knows
two different types of requests.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Simple requests:</p>

<p> A request that only uses <code>GET</code> or <code>POST</code>. If <code>POST</code> is used to send data to the server, the content type of the data
sent to the server with the HTTP <code>POST</code> request is one of <code>application/x-www-form-urlencoded</code>, <code>multipart/form-data</code>
or <code>text/plain</code>. The request must not contain custom headers (such as <code>X-Modified</code>, etc.)</p></li>
<li><p>Preflighted requests</p>

<p> A request that uses methods other than <code>GET</code> or <code>POST</code>. Also, if <code>POST</code> is used to send request data with a
content type other than <code>application/x-www-form-urlencoded</code>, <code>multipart/form-data</code> or <code>text/plain</code>, e.g. if the
<code>POST</code> request sends an XML payload to the server using <code>application/xml</code> or <code>text/xml</code>, then the request is a
preflighted request. Furthermore if the request contains custom headers, it's preflighted.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Unlike simple requests, preflighted requests first send an HTTP <code>OPTIONS</code> request header to the resource on the other
domain, in order to determine whether the actual request is safe to send. Since the console uses <code>POST</code> with a
content type of <code>application/dmr-encoded</code> all requests are preflighted requests. This will be important when looking
at the server side.</p>

<p>Common to all requests is that the browser adds the request header <code>Origin</code>. The value of this header is the site
that served the page. For example, suppose a page on http://www.example-social-network.com attempts to access a
user's data in online-personal-calendar.com. If the browser implements CORS, the following request header would be sent:</p>

<pre><code>Origin: http://www.example-social-network.com
</code></pre>

<h2>Server</h2>

<p>It is up to the server to decide which origins are allowed. When the server accepts cross-origin requests, it sends an
<code>Access-Control-Allow-Origin</code> header in its response. The value of the header indicates what origin sites are allowed.
For example, a response to the previous request would contain the following:</p>

<pre><code>Access-Control-Allow-Origin: http://www.example-social-network.com.
</code></pre>

<p>For the JBoss AS this implies changes to the class <code>org.jboss.as.domain.http.server.DomainApiHandler</code>. This class
handles HTTP requests to the management API. The modified version accepts preflighted <code>OPTIONS</code> requests and sets the
relevant response headers.</p>

<h2>Authentication</h2>

<p>The console uses digest authentication. This must continue to work when doing cross-origin requests. By default,
in cross-origin <code>XMLHttpRequest</code> invocations, browsers will not send credentials. A specific flag called
<code>withCredentials</code> has to be set on the <code>XMLHttpRequest</code> object when it is invoked. Unfortunately GWTs implementation
of the JavaScript <code>XMLHttpRequest</code> object does
<a href="https://code.google.com/p/google-web-toolkit/issues/detail?id=7677">not yet implement</a> this flag. For the time being
we need to include <code>withCredentials</code> by ourselves.</p>

<p>The next challenge is to trigger the login dialog when accessing protected resources. Unfortunately when it comes to
authentication browsers handle CORS quite differently. There are some workarounds depending on which browser is used:</p>

<ul>
<li>Chrome <a href="http://blog.chromium.org/2011/06/new-chromium-security-features-june.html">prevents basic authentication from a different origin as a phishing attack</a> period.
The only way to get around that is to start Chrome using the command line option <code>--allow-cross-origin-auth-prompt</code>.</li>
<li>Firefox makes no problems when it comes to display the login dialog (well done guys!)</li>
<li>Safari won't show the login dialog. You can get around that by inserting a hidden <code>&lt;iframe&gt;</code> element linking to the
protected url. This will trigger the authentication popup and once the user has authenticated, you can execute direct
<code>XMLHttpRequests</code> as usual.</li>
<li>Internet Explorer somewhat support CORS in IE8 and IE9 using the <code>XDomainRequest</code> object (but has limitations).</li>
</ul>


<p>Finally there's an issue related to preflighted <code>OPTIONS</code> requests on the server side. According to the specification
those requests must exclude user credentials:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Otherwise, make a preflight request [...] with the following additional constraints:</p></p><p><pre><code>- Exclude user credentials.<br/></code></pre></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>W3C CORS specification</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/#cross-origin-request-with-preflight-0'>www.w3.org/TR/cors/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Hence these requests are blocked by the server with "401 Unauthorized". As a workaround the authenticators in the AS
code base must let pass preflighted <code>OPTIONS</code> requests.</p>

<h2>Status Quo</h2>

<p>At the moment a first preview of an independent console is available at
OpenShift: <a href="https://console-hpehl.rhcloud.com">https://console-hpehl.rhcloud.com</a>. Please note that you must have a
CORS enabled server instance running in order to connect from the console. You can build one by yourself using the
"cors" branch of the AS code base: <a href="https://github.com/hpehl/wildfly/tree/cors">https://github.com/hpehl/wildfly/tree/cors</a>.
Follow the steps in the <a href="https://github.com/hpehl/wildfly/tree/cors#readme">README</a> to build the server.</p>

<p>Due to the limitations regarding authentication and CORS, the solution described here will only work in Firefox and
Safari. If you want to use Chrome make sure to use the <code>--allow-cross-origin-auth-prompt</code> command line option.</p>

<h2>Client Library</h2>

<p>I stumbled upon an interesting project on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/pazguille/CORS">https://github.com/pazguille/CORS</a>. Seems to have support for IE8+,
offers an easy to use API and hides the awkward implementation details. I will evaluate this and try to make a GWT port.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
