<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: lunr | Harald Pehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/blog/categories/lunr/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-08T13:01:25+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hpehl.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harald Pehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harald.pehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search using lunr.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpehl.info/search-using-lunr-dot-js.html"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T21:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpehl.info/search-using-lunr-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I <a href="/moved-blog-to-github-pages.html">moved</a> my blog from Blogger to Octopress back in May 2013, I always missed a powerful and well integrated search feature. Octopress is a static site generator and has no database to be queried for searches. The default search is just a redirection to Google Custom Search. This navigates away from the blog site and comes with Google Ads.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Once in a while I was looking for an alternative for my blog. When we developed a local search for the WildFly Admin Console, we choosed <a href="http://lunrjs.com/">lunr.js</a>. Lunr.js is a simple full-text search in your browser. This seems also a reasonable fit for my blog. After some research I came accross <a href="https://github.com/yortz/octopress-lunr-js-search">octopress-lunr-js-search</a>. It's an Octopress plugin which generates a local search index. This index is used by a handful of scripts to implement a search-as-you-type feature.</p>

<p>When implementing the search, I basically followed the <a href="https://github.com/yortz/octopress-lunr-js-search#how-to-use">instructions</a> on the plugins website. However I did without the Jekyll asset plugin, because it would have meant a major reorganization of my blog. I decided to move the search to a modal dialog. This dialog is opened when you click on the little search icon in the header or press the shortcut (&#8984;+. / Ctrl+.). As you start typing, the search results will appear accordingly.</p>

<p>Give it a try and let me know if you like it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
