<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: github | Harald Pehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/blog/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hpehl.info/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-22T01:32:52+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hpehl.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Harald Pehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[harald.pehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moved Blog to GitHub Pages]]></title>
    <link href="http://hpehl.info/moved-blog-to-github-pages.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-02T13:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hpehl.info/moved-blog-to-github-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For over three years I was hosting my blog at Blogger.com. Although publishing was quite easy I never was really happy
with the layout and the support for customization.<!--more --></p>

<p>I was looking for a new provider to host my blog. In particular I wanted to</p>

<ul>
<li>write my posts using <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">markdown</a></li>
<li>be able to have regular pages (like projects, about me, ...)</li>
<li>have full control over the look and feel of my blog</li>
<li>have support for responsive design</li>
<li>host the blog with my own top level domain</li>
</ul>


<p>After some research I stumbled across <a href="http://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> in combination
with <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> and <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>. The setup is really easy and there are
plenty of resources and documentation around Jekyll and Octopress.</p>

<p>As my blog contains a manageable number of posts, I decided to manually migrate them to markdown. But there is also
support for <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/blog-migrations#blogger-blogspot">automatic migration</a>. I didn't
migrate the comments of my blog and started from scratch using <a href="http://disqus.com/">Disqus</a>.</p>

<p>I invested quite some time on the look and feel for my new blog. To a great extent I was inspired by
the <a href="https://github.com/amelandri/darkstripes">darkstripes</a> theme and the blog
of <a href="http://melandri.net/">Alessandro Melandri</a>. My navigation was influenced by the website
of <a href="http://www.thibaultjorge.com/en">Thibault Jorge</a>.</p>

<p>The result of the migration is what you're looking at. I hope you like it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
